<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Living testimonies concerning the death of the righteous. Or The blessed end of Joseph Featherstone and Sarah his daughter; written by Sarah his wife, and Thomas Browne her second husband; not unworthy the knowledge of friends and their posterity; that all may be incouraged to live well, that their latter end may be blessed. Also something concerning Charles Wray, Grace Browne, and Katharine Browne her daughter, writ by Thomas Browne the elder, in Partney in the county of Lincoln. All of them being a sweet favour of life, laid down their heads in peace</title>
            <author>Featherstone, Sarah, of Partney-Mills, Lincolnshire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F576B</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827040</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">207475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1884:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Living testimonies concerning the death of the righteous. Or The blessed end of Joseph Featherstone and Sarah his daughter; written by Sarah his wife, and Thomas Browne her second husband; not unworthy the knowledge of friends and their posterity; that all may be incouraged to live well, that their latter end may be blessed. Also something concerning Charles Wray, Grace Browne, and Katharine Browne her daughter, writ by Thomas Browne the elder, in Partney in the county of Lincoln. All of them being a sweet favour of life, laid down their heads in peace</title>
                  <author>Featherstone, Sarah, of Partney-Mills, Lincolnshire.</author>
                  <author>Browne, Thomas, of Partney. aut</author>
                  <author>Wray, Charles, member of the Society of Friends. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Sowle: and sold at the Three-Kyes [sic] in Nags-Head. [sic] Court in Grace-Church-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication conjectured by cataloger.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Featherstone, Joseph, d. 1682 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Featherstone, Sarah, 1673-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Browne, Grace, ca. 1634-1682 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Browne, Katharine, 1663 or 4-1680 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIVING TESTIMONIES Concerning the <hi>Death of the Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR The bleſſed End of <hi>Joſeph Featherſtone</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> his Daughter; Written by <hi>Sarah</hi> his Wife, and <hi>Thomas Browne</hi> her ſecond Husband; Not unworthy the knowledge of Friends and their Poſterity; that all may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to Live well, that their lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End may be Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſomething concerning <hi>Charles Wray, Grace Browne,</hi> and <hi>Katharine Browne</hi> her Daughter, Writ by <hi>Thomsa Browne</hi> the Elder, in <hi>Partney</hi> in the County of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All of them being a ſweet ſavour of Life, laid down their Heads in Peace.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Andrew Sowle:</hi> And ſold at the <hi>Three-Kyes</hi> in <hi>Nags-Head. Court</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:207475:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207475:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Curteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Enſuing Teſtimonies are ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly recommended to thy ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Peruſual, with an earneſt deſire thou may'ſt Read them in Meekneſs, and the Fear of God; and if a Parent, wait upon the Lord in his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Heavenly Gift, to receive that Wiſdom which is truly profitable to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thee, and to endue with a right Underſtanding, and a godly Care and Zeal to Train up thy Child in the Fear of God, and Admonition of the Lord; and not only to Admoniſh thy Child to that which is Good, and not to follow or delight in the fooliſh Faſhions and vain Dreſſes of the evil World, but alſo while under thy care to Feed, Cloth and Provide for, to reſtrain from thoſe things which are unbecoming the Truth and our holy Profeſſion thereof, and not to lay out and exſpend thy Subſtance which God hath made thee a Steward of, to gratifie that mind in thy Child, which thou haſt known and felt the Judgment of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207475:3"/> the Lord to be executed upon in thy ſelf, becauſe it was not ſubject unto the Law of God, neither indeed can be; and therefore ought not to be given way unto in thy Child, nor comply'd with by thee, leaſt thou become guilty of thy Childs hurt, to the diſhonour of Truth, and thy own Grief; but rather then thus humour thy Child, let the like care be on thee, as was upon our Deceaſed <hi>Friend,</hi> who on his dying-Bed, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Deſired that his Child ſhould be brought up in the Nurture and Fear of the Lord, and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Plain and Decent parts or things that belong to a Woman,</hi>
                  <hi> But upon a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Seam, nor any thing Superfluous, not to lift her Hand to do, for that,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>will bring Diſhonour to the bleſſed Truth, and be a Burden to the Simple-hearted:</hi>
               </q> Obſerve the Godly Care of this good Man: Oh, that many Parents may be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the like Godly Care and zeal for the Education of their tender Off-ſpring.</p>
            <p>And now, oh, Curteous <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou art young, and not yet become the Parent of Children, Read in Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Fear of God, the following Teſtimony concerning theſe young Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207475:3"/> who may be truly eſteemed as <hi>wiſe Virgins,</hi> and ſuch that had more regard to the inward then the outward Adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby they became ſo Comly, and their Converſation ſo Commendable and Examplary, that <hi>Sarah Featherſtone,</hi> its ſaid, was not one that had only a Love to faithful <hi>Friends,</hi> and their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Meetings,</hi> but alſo when there, was preſerved out of Drowſineſs, Sleepineſs and Heavineſs, <hi>(which over took the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Virgins, ſo that their Lamps went out, and they were unfit to enter with the Bride-Groom)</hi> but ſhe ſat in Meetings in a ſweet frame of Spirit, and was often tendred in the Meetings, a thing very commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Young and Old: She alſo when ſhe was ſent abroad to be Educated, was careful to improve her Time, a thing worthy of Praiſe and of thy Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for with Grief may it be ſaid, there are too many Children, that when their Parents ſend them abroad to be Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and are at great Charge and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence by reaſon thereof, they too to much neglect that which their Parents ſend them forth to Learn, and in Play, Wildneſs and Idleneſs ſquander away
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207475:4"/> their pretious Time, often talking what Portions they have, or their Parents can give them, and obſerving what this and the other wears, and how this and the other Dreſſes themſelves, and then endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do the like, and thus ſtir up one another to that which is Evil; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by giving way to this Evil mind, come to have a proud Look, which is an Abomination to the Lord, and a Lying Tongue, which he hates. Oh, therefore who-ever thou art, which Reads theſe and the following Lines, conſider ſeriouſly theſe things, and remember thou muſt Dye and come to Judgment; and though thou art Young, yet knoweſt not how ſoon thy change may come, and thy Body muſt return to the Duſt, and become Meat for the Worms: Therefore while time laſts improve it, and mind the Grace and good Spirit of God in thy own Heart, hearken and return at the Reproofs of it, that thou may'ſt know and be led in the way of Life, and become a Comfort to thy Parents, and a Companion of them that fear the Lord, and rejoycing to thy Friends, who have no greater Joy then to behold their Children walking in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207475:4"/> Truth, the which Truth and Spirit of it, if thou wilt love and obey, it will lead thee to make a right improvement of thy time, to be Obedient to thy Parents, and Subject to thy Tutors, to be meek and lowly in thy mind, and to be affraid to commit that which is Evil, though in a ſecret Corner, or to wear that which is needleſs or ſuperfluous; for this Truth is that which will teach thee all things, if thou wilt learn of it, thou wilt become more Excellent then thy Neighbours, and wilt not be ſeduced by the way of the Wicked, nor let thy mind out after their vain and fooliſh Faſhions, nor delight in their evil Practices and proud Dreſſes, and falſe Speech, and corrupt Communication, but in the ſingle Language, the plain and decent Dreſſes and Apparel that the godly of Old were, and now are Adorned in.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Field.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>September</hi> the <hi>26th</hi> 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:207475:5"/>
            <head>There hath ſomething lain as a weight upon my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for ſometime, to write this Teſtimony as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Concerning my dear <hi>Deceaſed</hi> Husband <hi>Joſeph Featherſtone, for the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall be had in Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Remembrance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AND this I can truly ſay concerning him, that he was a Man whom the Lord had endued with much Wiſdom and Meekneſs, as his mind came to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired inward to wait upon the Lord, his Strength was daily renewed; and when the Lord was pleaſed to reveal his Son in him, then did the Lord wonderfully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for him, and by a ſtrong Hand brought him out of <hi>Egypt's</hi> Darkneſs, and from under the Hand of the Enemy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207475:5"/> of his Soul, who would not be willing that he ſhould go forth to ſerve the Lord his God. Oh the deep Exerciſe of the Travel of his Soul for Days and Months, when he went bowed down under the weight of his Sins, then they that were his Teachers before, could ſpeak no Peace to his wounded Soul, for they were Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians of no value: Oh the Sence of the Lords great Love to his Travelling Soul, how he brought him through the Wilderneſs, and from off the barren Mountains; and bore up his head above many Temptations and Trials within and without, and ſet his Feet upon a Rock, and eſtabliſhed his goings; ſo that he could call to his Neighbours and Acquaintance to come and taſte how good the Lord is to them that wait upon him; and many a time could ſpeak a Word in ſeaſon to ſuch as were ſeeking the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving amongſt the Dead; and his circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Walking reached the Hearts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for he loved Truth in the inward parts, and to do the Will of the Lord was his great delight: He was Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of Gods Everlaſting Truth, the Twenty ninth Year of his Age, whom
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207475:6"/> the Lord made Inſtrumental in his Hand towards my Convincement; he was a true Yoke-fellow indeed, his Company to me was very dear, and my Soul hath often been refreſhed in his ſavoury Life, which hath cauſed my loſs of ſo dear a Husband, and ſo true a help-meet to be the greater, but knowing it to be of the Lord, I deſire to be ſubmitted to his bleſſed Will, that he alone may have the Glory of his own Works, for he is worthy who is God bleſſed for ever. In the time of his Sickneſs the Lord was pleaſed to bear him up in much Patience, and he was freely given up to the Will of the Lord; the day aſter he fell Sick, I ſitting by him, he perceiving I was much troubled, he ſaid, <hi>Dear heart, give me up to the Will of the Lord,</hi> for ſaid he, <hi>I can freely give up all;</hi> and when ſome Friends came to viſit him, he Exhorted them to Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>And then the Lord would make a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Bed Comfortable to them;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>though he felt much Sickneſs and Pain upon his Body, yet the Refreſhments that he felt from the Lord, made all his Troubles eaſie;</hi> then he ſpoke many comfortable Words to me, ſaying, <hi>How good the Lord had been
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207475:6"/> to us in many Exerciſes and Tryals, and through his great Love bore up our heads a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them all;</hi> and his Prayers was to the Lord, <hi>that we might be preſerved in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fear and undefiled Way, to bear a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the bleſſed Truth, to the end of our days:</hi> And then he deſired me that his dear Child ſhould be brought up in the Nurture and Fear of the Lord, and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the plain and decent Parts that belongeth to a Woman, but upon a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Seam, nor any thing ſuperfluous, no not to lift her hand to do, for that ſaid he, <hi>Will bring diſhonour to the bleſſed Truth, and be a Burthen to the ſimple-Hearted, and draw out the minds of the young ones after Vanity, which thing,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>my Soul ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</hi> The day before he was taken away, he ſeemed to be ſomething reſtleſs, I ſaid, dear Heart, thou art Reſtleſs; then he with a chearful Countenance ſaid, <hi>Do'ſt thou not know where the Weary go to Reſt;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>my Reſt and Fellowſhip is with the Lord:</hi> Some Friends came to Viſit him, who asked how it was with him, he ſaid, <hi>I am well, I feel no Sickneſs;</hi> and told them, <hi>he was glad to ſee them, and was much Refreſhed in his Spirit;</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207475:7"/> many ſweet Refreſhments from the Lord ran through him, to the great Comfort and Refreſhment of the honeſt-Hearted; then he deſired to be alone, ſaying, <hi>I would ſee if I could get a little Sleep,</hi> and ſo reſted a pretty time; and then I asked him, how he felt himſelf, he ſaid, <hi>I am well bleſſed be the Lord,</hi> and deſired me to be ſatisfied, for he was ſatisfied, and lifting up his Hands, ſaid, <hi>O Lord, thou art the Eternal God,</hi> and ſo fell aſleep in the Lord, where he is gone far above the reach of his Perſecutors, to praiſe the Lord that ſits upon the Throne, and the Lamb for evermore; in the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſence thereof my Soul doth praiſe and Magnifie the Lord on his behalf, who counted him worthy to ſuffer for his Name ſake, by bearing a faithful Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Hireling Prieſts,</hi> who like devouring Wolves ſeek to lay Waſte Gods Heritage</p>
            <p>And now having ſomewhat eaſed my Spirit, I humbly deſire of the Lord, that he would be pleaſed to bear me up through all my Exerciſes and Tryals, that he may be pleaſed to ſuffer me to be tryed withal; and to endue me with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207475:7"/> Wiſdom and Underſtanding to govern my dear Child and Family in his moſt holy Fear and undefiled Way, to the Praiſe of his moſt holy Name, <hi>Amen;</hi> That when time ſhall be here no more, I may have a Reſting-place with the Lord for evermore.</p>
            <q>He departed this Life, the <hi>26th</hi> day of the <hi>9th</hi> Month, 1682. in <hi>Poſtland,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Crowland;</hi> and was Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the <hi>27th</hi> day in <hi>Friends-Burying-place</hi> in <hi>Crowland,</hi> being Accompanied with a pretty many Friends, Relations and Neighbours.</q>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Poſtland</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Crowland,</hi> being the place of my Abode,
<date>the 12th of the 3d Month, 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sarah Featherſtone.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:207475:8"/>
            <head>A brief Relation of the Life and Death of my dear and only Child, <hi>Sarah Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſtone,</hi> a Maid of the Age of fifteen years wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one Month; who Departed this Life at <hi>Partney-Mills</hi> in <hi>Lincoln-Shire,</hi> the <hi>17th</hi> day of the <hi>7th</hi> Month, 1688.</head>
            <p>THere hath a weight lain upon my Spirit for ſome time, to Write this Teſtimony concerning my dear and only Child: <hi>For the Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſting Remembrance;</hi> and truly it was the Lords great Love to me in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me this dear Child, which I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as a great Bleſſing; but that which is chiefly in my Eye, was the Lords great Love to her, who had inclined her Heart
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207475:8"/> to hear Wiſdoms Voice, which often calleth to the young Ones, <hi>To remember their Creator in the days of their Youth;</hi> and Bleſſed are they that hear and obey in their meaſure, and with meek <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe rather to ſuffer Afflictions with the <hi>Children of God,</hi> then to enjoy the Pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon. And bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord for ever, who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined her Heart to Love, Serve and Fear him from her tender years; for from a Child ſhe was tender and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, in true Submiſſion and Obedience to her Parents, ſo that I know not that in her young time, that we ever had any juſt cauſe to uſe the Rod, for ſhe was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tender-Hearted, and of a comely Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, kind and courteous to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of a meek and quiet Spirit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beloved of moſt that did know her. Her dear Father Departed this Life when ſhe was about nine years of Age, who deſired upon his dying-Bed, <q rend="margQuotes">That his dear <hi>Child</hi> ſhould be brought up in the Nurture and Fear of the Lord, and be Educated in the plain and decent parts that belong to a Woman, but upon a needleſs Seam, nor upon any
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207475:9"/> thing Superfluous, no not to lift her Hand to do, for that ſaith he, will bring Diſhonour to the bleſſed Truth, and be a burthen to the ſimple-Hearted, and draw out the minds of the young Ones after Vanity, which thing, ſaith he, my<hi>Soul hateth;</hi> 
               </q> and his Breathings was to the Lord, that we might be perſerved in his moſt holy Fear, and undefiled Way to the end of our days; and bleſſed be the Lord for ever, who giveth Underſtanding and Wiſdom to them that fear him; and is a ſure Help in the time of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them that wait upon him; and in this my great Exerciſe in parting with ſo dear and tender a Husband, and ſo true a Help-meet; my dear Child was a great Comfort and Bleſſing unto me, and was very loving and tender over me, ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing moſt of her equals that I knew of; &amp; as ſhe did grow up in years, was a good Example in our Family, for her harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Life and loving Behaviour appeared to the World what Stock ſhe was of, but more eſpecially her dear and tender Love to faithful Friends, of which ſhe ever had a good eſteem, and would mind me often of the Want of poor Friends and others,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207475:9"/> And ſhe her ſelf would be helpful in what ſhe had of her own, when need required; for her Life and Delight was in doing good, and in that ſhe reached the better part in all, and from a Child ſhe did take great delight in going to Meetings, and was much preſerved out of heavineſs, or having her eye abroad, but ſitting in a ſweet frame of Spirit, and would often be tendred in a Meeting, which hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten refreſhed my heart in the great Love of the Lord, and to him be the Glory and Honour over all his own Works for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen</hi> ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <p>And when I Married the ſecond time, the Innocency of my dear Child did much appear in her Tenderneſs and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to us her Parents, and her love to all ſhe came amongſt, for her Life was in Peace, and could not abide Diſcord ſhould have place in any: And when ſhe went abroad to be Educated, ſhe would be very careful in improving her time, and was a good Example where ſhe went, amongſt Friends and others, and hath left a good ſavour behind her, and her removal hath tendred the hearts of many that did know her; and when my dear
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207475:10"/> Husband was taken to Priſon from me and his tender Family, ſhe was a true Simpathizer with me, many times wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take part with me in my Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, for ſhe was very dear and tender over me, willing to be governed by me, and to take up the croſs to her own will in any thing I could not allow of for her to wear or do; and her dear Fathers dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Words did take deep impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her heart, and though Temptations ſometimes did lie near, yet through the Lords great Love to her, her heart was kept low, and ſhe with <hi>Mary</hi> choſe the better part, which ſhall never be taken from her; ſo that I am ſatisfied that her Life was not in thoſe periſhing things; in which my heart is often refreſhed and comforted, and the remembrance of her is made ſweet to me; for through the Lords great Love to her, I know not any that can charge her with any wrong done to them, either by word or deed, for her life and delight was in Innocency and Love, adorned with Meekneſs. Oh, the conſideration of my great loſs of ſo dear a Child now in my old Age, hath cauſed me ſometimes to ſay in my heart
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207475:10"/> if <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Abſolom, would God I had dyed for thee, O</hi> Abſolom <hi>my Son!</hi> ſurely I have far more cauſe then <hi>David</hi> had, I having no more of my own to be a Comfort to me, (this being the laſt of Ten, Nine of them were Buried before her Father) whoſe old Exerciſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord is pleaſed to renew, but when I conſider of Eternity, and the Joy that they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into; and how good the Lord hath been to me in the days of my Afflictions, and hath born up my head above all my Sorrows, and that they are taken away from the evil to come; in this I am ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, believing that my loſs is their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting gain, and that I ſhall go to them as I in faithfulneſs abide.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventh Month on the ninth day, about the eleventh hour of the night, it pleaſed the Lord to viſit my dear Child with this Sickneſs whereon ſhe dyed, and when my maid came and told me my Child was taken Sick, my heart was much troubled, and it ſeiſed upon me very deeply, that my dear Child would be taken from me; and when I came at my Child ſhe did lie in a ſweet frame of Spirit, under a great weight of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207475:11"/> and when I had been with her ſome time, ſhe told me, <hi>ſhe thought ſhe ſhould be taken from me,</hi> which cauſed my Exerciſe every way to be the greater, but to the Will of the Lord I was brought who gave me her, and he alone was worthy to diſpoſe of her as he pleaſeth; and ſo my dear Child did lie in a ſweet frame of Spirit, often breathing to the Lord to bear her up above all her troubles, and did ſpeak little to us, but her weakneſs increaſed daily upon her, and much pain, which this dear Babe endured with much patience; and when we would have ſent for a <hi>Doctor,</hi> ſhe would not, but ſaid, <hi>ſhe was freely given up to the Will of the Lord, whether to live or dye;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>dear Mother, give me ſuch things as thou thinkeſt convenient for me, that I am able to take, for I am weak;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it hath been laid before me ſometime, that I was not of a long Life, and if this be the time of my Change I am content;</hi> and ſo did lie ſtill, not ſeeming to be concerned at any thing, but keeping her mind in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, often breathing to the Lord to bear her up above her weakneſs, and to be her ſupport to the end of her days;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207475:11"/> my heart would often be bowed down and tendred when I did ſee her under the great weight of her Sickneſs, at which ſhe would be troubled; and ſay, <hi>dear Mother, thy dear and tender love to me hath been very great, and in that Love I deſire we may reſt, freely given up to the Will of the Lord, for the Lord may not ſee it meet to truſt me in this wicked World any longer;</hi> and then ſhe ſaid, <hi>dear Mother, who would deſire to live in this abominable wicked World any longer? Oh, the abominable Pride of this wicked World; and there is ſome amongſt us, which can take liberty to faſhion them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in many things like unto the World, both in their Habit, and other needleſs things; Oh, but the Chriſtian Life is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing; this is not the adorning we are to put on, for if the Righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the Wicked and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear?</hi> then ſhe did lie ſtill for ſome time whilſt the violence of the Feaver troubled her much; and then ſhe ſaid, <hi>Ah, my dear Mother, in all my Sickneſs that I have had, I never felt the like I think, but I hope the Lord will be pleaſed to bear me up above all my troubles to the end of my days; Ah, my dear Father, never ſo ſick in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207475:12"/> my Life; Oh, ſick at my heart,</hi> which often tendred our hearts, to ſee our dear Child paſs through theſe great troubles at ſome times; and then ſhe would ſay, <hi>Oh Lord in mercy remember me, and bear me up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all my Afflictions, for my heart truſteth in thee;</hi> I ſaid, my dear Child, if the Lord ſhould be pleaſed to take thee from me, where haſt thou a deſire to be Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wilt thou be Buried by thy dear Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in Friends Burying-place, in <hi>Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> where we came from? ſhe ſaid, <hi>I have ſome thoughts formerly to have been Buried by my dear Father, but conſidering the greatneſs of the Journey, and ſo many Buried near him, I am ſatisfied, I leave it to thee and my Father;</hi> I ſaid, my dear Child, art thou willing to be Buried in our Burying-place, where I hope to be Buried by thee; ſhe ſaid, <hi>dear Mother, Bury me where thou and my Father pleaſeth, I leave it to you, its no matter how many Miles diſtance theſe Bodies lies, our Souls ſhall one day rejoyce together;</hi> then I asked her, what ſhe would have diſpoſed of, of that which was hers, ſhe ſaid, <hi>I would have my poor Relations have ſomething, and poor Friends Children where we came from,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207475:12"/> what thee and my Father pleaſeth, I leave it to you, for my Father is a good Man, and hath been very tender over me, and my Love to him hath been very dear;</hi> and then ſhe ſaid, <hi>dear Mother, do not trouble me with any thing, but let us be ſubmitted to the Will of the Lord in all things, do not ſpeak to me, nor give me any thing without I deſire it;</hi> and ſo lay ſtill in a ſweet frame of Spirit, and with as ſweet a Countenance, and as chearful as if ſhe had no ſuch Weakneſs upon her, only ſometimes a great trouble in her head, which the Lord was pleaſed to bear her up in much patience to paſs through, not a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented word was heard to paſs from her, but true Contentedneſs in much Patience, often ſaying, <hi>Ah, my dear and heavenly Father come away, come away, for my heart truſteth in thee:</hi> ſome time before ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted her Speech failed her, after which a ſweet harmony often ran through her, often lifting up her Hands with a very chearful Countenance, and ſo ſhe fell a ſleep in the Lord; who I then felt a ſtay to my mind, living Praiſes to his moſt holy and powerful Name, who is a God of endleſs Mercies; my Spirit was much comforted in the Lord in the behalf
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207475:13"/> of my dear Child in the time of her Sickneſs, who endued her with much patience, and wonderfully bore her up above all her Sickneſs and Pain which was upon her Body, at ſometimes not knowing where to lay her Head to have a little eaſe, which ſhe through the great love of the Lord was born up in much patience to paſs through, in true ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his bleſſed Will, and I do believe is at reſt with God her Maker, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended above all her Sorrows and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, to praiſe the Lord that ſits upon the Throne, and the Lamb for evermore; in the undoubted ſence of which my Soul doth Praiſe and Magnifie the Lord on her behalf, and indeed the ſame doth out-ballance the great loſs I have of her as to the outward, well knowing my Loſs is her everlaſting Gain; and deſiring that I may be ſubject to the Will of the Lord, in what he may be pleaſed to try me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and that he may have the Glory of his own Works, for he is worthy who gave me her, and now hath taken her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Bleſſed and Praiſed be his moſt holy Name for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Partney-Mills</hi> the place of my abode the
<date> the <hi>20th</hi> of the <hi>12th</hi> Month, 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed> Sarah Brown Her Mother.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:207475:13"/>
               <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>SInce I writ this Teſtimony concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my dear Child, there hath often freſh ſprings of the Lords great Love concerning her aroſe in my Heart which I had omitted my Duty in; when this Child was in the eleventh year of her age, it pleaſed the Lord to ſuffer Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution to come upon us (for the tryal of our Faith) for Meeting together and Worſhiping God as he requires, that is in Spirit and in Truth; we being at a Meeting about eight Miles from our outward Dwelling, the Meeting being ended, and Friends ready to depart, ſome in the yard, ſome in the high-way, comes two Informers after a very rude manner, calling of us Rogues and Whores, and Swearing deſperately to many untruths, my Husband reproved one of them (called <hi>Chipſam)</hi> for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207475:14"/> Swearing, he was very angry, and held up his Stick, and ſaid, <hi>He would break his Head, did he tell him, he was the Kings Officer.</hi> [Obſerve, the ſaid <hi>Chipſam</hi> was not long after carried to <hi>Linclon</hi> Goal for Debt, and their dyed, and was there buried after a very mean manner in the Caſtle yard, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> But before the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fell to be there again by courſe, which was a Month, (they had made much ſpoil of Friends Goods) it pleaſed the Lord to viſit my dear Husband with much Weakneſs, ſo that we could not go to the Meeting; but my dear Child having a great deſire to go again with her Brothers, we wear freely willing, and they had a peaceable Meeting, and Friends ready to depart as before, came the ſame Informers as rude or worſe then before, and within a few days Levied my Husbands Goods again upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of one of his Sons, but ſhe being under Age, they could take nothing from her Father in Law upon her account, at which ſhe ſeemed to be troubled, (ſhe having a conſiderable Portion in his hand) and ſaid, <hi>If they be ſuffered to take all that my Father hath, he ſhall not want to give up to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:207475:14"/> ſerve the Lord ſo long as I have any thing,</hi> (and would ſometimes ſay to me, <hi>I do believe I ſhall never want any good thing which the Lord ſees convenient for me)</hi> in which ſhe manifeſted her Love to him upon her dying Bed, as it is fully decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the fore-going Teſtimony; ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eaſed my Spirit, and diſcharged my Duty which I did owe, I deſire to reſt in Peace with the Lord, and in Love to his Truth and People, to the end of my days and time here in this mortal World, ſo that when time here will be no more, I may lay down my Head in Peace, as my dear Child hath done; and then as ſhe ſaid upon her dying Bed, <hi>Our Souls ſhall rejoyce together.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Written at <hi>Partney: Mills</hi>
                     <date>
                        <hi>the 11th</hi> of the <hi>3d</hi> Month, 1689.</date> by</dateline>
                  <signed>Sarah Brown.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:207475:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thomas Brown</hi> his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony concerning his dear Daughter-in-Law <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah Featherſtone.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Teſtimony I have to bear con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my dear Friend and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Sarah Featherſtone,</hi> firſt let me ſay ſomething of her outward Abilities; ſhe was Born of honeſt Parents, and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the plain and decent parts, her dear Mother thought convenient, as Sowing, Kniting, Reading, Writing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which ſhe exceeded moſt of her equals, ſhe was Womanly about Buſineſs, and what ſhe did ſhe did it with all her might; ſhe was of a ſingular good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of a comely, chearful, quiet, modeſt Countenance, ripe Wit, quick of Apprehenſion, mild and loving Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to all, and eſpecially to Friends, but more eſpecially to them that were poor; at Monthly Meetings when Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:207475:15"/> Friends had Contributions for the ſervice of Truth, this dear Child would freely throw in her Mite; a poor Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow Friend uſe to come to our Houſe, when ſhe went away, if this dear Child did not ſee her, ſhe would ſometimes run after her, (not like <hi>Gehazi)</hi> and give her ſomething ſhe had of her own, as ſometimes half a dozen Eggs, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a tender regard ſhe had to the Poor; her dear Father dyed when ſhe was about nine years old, and after a convenient time her dear Mother became my Wife, ſo I had a certain knowledge of her for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix years, in which time I cannot remember that ſhe ever gave me one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry word, but was as loving and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to me as though ſhe had been my own Child; I was carried to Priſon for bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Teſtimony againſt Tythes, and there the Lord was pleaſed to viſit me with Sickneſs and other great Troubles, in which time this dear Child came ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times to viſit me, though the Journey was long and difficult ſometimes, but her dear and tender Love to me out-ballanced it all. This dear Child ever ſince I did know her, had a great deſire to go to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207475:16"/> Friends Meetings; I never ſee her in the leaſt concerned in ſleep or heavineſs, but when I looked upon her I found her in a ſober and weighty frame of Spirit, which often cauſed my Heart to rejoyce, and the remembrance of her is very ſweet to me at this time. When the Lord was pleaſed to viſit her with this Sickneſs whereon ſhe dyed, which was in the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of her Age, ſhe bore it with great Patience, conſidering the violence of the Diſtemper (it was a very high Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) of which ſhe lay juſt a Week, in which time ſhe would often breath unto the Lord, and ſay, <hi>Ah Lord help me;</hi> and ſay, <hi>Ah dear Father, what muſt I do? Ah, dear Mother, what muſt I do; never ſo ſick in all my Life?</hi> we tenderly exhorted her to keep her mind ſtayed upon the Lord, then ſhe would lie ſtill a pretty while, whil'ſt the violence of the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſorely troubled her, then ſhe would cry out as before, and ſay, <hi>Ah Lord help me;</hi> and ſeveral times did lift up her hands and ſay, <hi>Lord have mercy upon me, Ah Lord help me;</hi> thus this patient inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Lamb finiſhed her Teſtimony in a good day, and I do verily believe is at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207475:16"/> reſt with the Lord for evermore; this dear Babe, which was the only Child of her tender Mother, Departed this Life the ſeventeenth day of the ſeventh Month 1688. about mid night, and was honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Buried the twentieth day following at <hi>Tumby-Wood</hi> ſide, in the Pariſh of <hi>Lirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> upon the Bain, in <hi>Friends Burning-Place,</hi> being accompanied with pretty many <hi>Friends, Relations</hi> and <hi>Neighbours</hi> unto the ſaid place, where there was gathered together a pretty many <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Neighbours,</hi> where we had a good Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing held by our very dear and well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Friend <hi>John Whitehead,</hi> who very tenderly accompanied us thither, where we were livingly refreſhed together, for there was Milk for Babes, and Meat for them of riper Age, with living Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies concerning the ſober Life and harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Converſation of this innocent Child, by our dear Friend <hi>John Whitehead</hi> (who had certain knowledge of her) ſhe being ſometimes before Tabled at his Houſe) and <hi>William Birks</hi> likewiſe, ſhe having been at his Houſe a pretty time, a little before ſhe fell Sick, was conſtrained to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:207475:17"/> bring in his publick Teſtimony concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this dear Child, all which greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed and comforted us her Relations, and was of good ſervice to the whole Meeting, and may be a ſweet ſavour to Generations to come; much more I might ſay concerning this dear Child as to her ſober and loving Behaviour to all; her comlineſs in her Apparel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (who like meek <hi>Moſes)</hi> choſe rather to ſuffer Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions with the diſpiſed People of God in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> then to enjoy the pleaſures of Sin for a ſeaſon, and did truly (I believe) remember her Creator in the days of her youth; this is Written for this and Generations to come, to ſtand upon Record, that young People may conſider their latter end, and whilſt they have time prize it; Written in love to the Lord, his Truth and People, having had a weight upon my Spirit for ſome Months, and now having eaſed my mind, and done my Duty which I did owe, I deſire to reſt in Peace; And if I in this, or at any other time, have ſaid or done any thing that may tend to Gods Glory, or be ſerviceable to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207475:17"/> any, my real deſire is, that he alone may have the Glory, Honour and the Praiſe, for he alone is worthy, not only at this time but henceforth and for evermore, <hi>Amen</hi> ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Partney-Mills
<date>the <hi>4th</hi> day of the <hi>11th</hi> Month, 1688, 89.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thomas Brown, Which was her Father in Law.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:207475:18"/>
            <head>Some Teſtimonies; Concerning <hi>Charles Wray, Grace Brown</hi> and <hi>Katharine Brown</hi> her Daughter, Writ by <hi>Thomas Brown</hi> the Elder, in <hi>Partney</hi> in the County of <hi>Lincoln;</hi> who all dyed in the Faith, and left a ſweet ſavour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them; the ſaid <hi>Charles Wray</hi> having received a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Gift, which he exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed to Gods glory, and the refreſhment of his People.</head>
            <p>SOmething lies weightily upon my mind, and hath done for ſeveral Months, to Write as a Teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our dear Friend <hi>Charles Wray,</hi> being one that was very well acquainted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:207475:18"/> with him for ſeveral years, I thought it my Duty to mention ſomething concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his tender care over the Church of Chriſt while amongſt us; he was taken from us in the flower of his Years, the Lord was pleaſed to take him away (as he hath done many honeſt <hi>Friends</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and ſince) from the evil to come; he was Servant to me about half a year, (and Tenant to me about twelve years) in which time he was very ſerviceable to me and my dear Wife as to our Convince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not only by his Words, but by his wiſe Walking; he met with great Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in his time, but the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to carry him through it all, and make him inſtrumental in his Hand, to the ſtrengthning of the weak, for the Lord was pleaſed to open his Mouth to declare of his great love to Mankind, in which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was his chief delight; towards the latter end of his time the Lord was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to viſit him with weakneſs of Body, ſo that he lay in Bed ſome Weeks, in which time I went ſeveral times to viſit him, and was very much refreſhed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the Preſence of the Lord did attend him; In his Weakneſs he was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207475:19"/> very Comfortable both to <hi>Friends</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for he could ſpeak a Word in ſeaſon to moſt Conditions; the Lord was pleaſed in the time of his Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſend two of his Meſſengers amongſt us, and he having a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee them, they with ſome <hi>Friends</hi> went one Evening to viſit him, and we had a heavenly Meeting together, for the Power and Preſence of the Lord was plentifully manifeſted amongſt us, and our Weak Brother, whom I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, was at that time made Strong, to declare of the Goodneſs of the Lord, and to praiſe his moſt holy Name, to the great comfort and refreſhment of the Faithful; he often deſired of the Lord that he would be pleaſed to endue him with a good Underſtanding to the end of his days, and lay no more upon him then he would give him Patience to bear, all which the Lord (in his great Love and Mercy) was pleaſed to anſwer, Praiſes to his moſt holy and powerful Name for evermore, <hi>Amen</hi> ſaith my Soul<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for he did ſpeak ſenſible Words a little before he departed, and was born up with much Patience all the time
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:207475:19"/> of his Weakneſs; he ſaid to a <hi>Friend</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before his Death, <hi>That the Candle did burn dim,</hi> and preſently departed without either Sob or Groan that was heard; he remembred his Creator in his young time, and made his peace with God whil'ſt here, and now is gone to receive the Fruits of his Labours, and to reſt with the Lord for evermore; ſo hoping I have done my Duty which I did owe, and eaſed my Spirit, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to reſt in peace with the Lord in whom is my chief delight.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Partney</hi>
                  <date>the Tenth day of the Eleventh Month, 1682.</date>
               </dateline> By
<signed>Thomas Brown the Elder. </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:207475:20"/>
            <head>I felt a weight laid upon me to Write this Teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my dear and truely loving Wife <hi>Grace Brown,</hi> whom the Lord hath been pleaſed to take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</head>
            <p>THis I can ſay, ſhe had an honeſt deſire after the Lord in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of her days, as I may ſay early, when I had little in my mind that was good, ſhe did often breath unto the Lord for me, and my dear Child <hi>Elia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> likewiſe; (who was a Loving, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Obedient Child to us both, whom the Lord hath been pleaſed to take to himſelf likewiſe, about a eleven days before her dear Mother) and he was pleaſed to hear their Cries and Tears, and change my mind to that which was good and acceptable to himſelf, Praiſes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:207475:20"/> to his Powerful Name for evermore, <hi>Amen</hi> ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <p>We were both Convinced of Gods precious Truth about the year 1669. Our dear Friends <hi>John Whitehead</hi> and <hi>Charles Wray</hi> were very tender over us, being chief Inſtruments in the hand of the Lord towards our Convincement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhe was a true, faithful and loving Wife to me, a true yoke-Fellow, a help-Meet indeed, Zealous for God and his Truth, which was very precious to her, which ſhe delighted in more then any thing in this World; ſhe was freely given up to the Will of the Lord, and bore things with great Patience, to the admiration of ſome in the time of my Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Lincoln-Caſtle,</hi> where I was thrown in by a Hireling-Prieſt for bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Teſtimony againſt Tythes; whom ſhe bore a faithful Teſtimony againſt (when he ſent his Wife to demand Tythes, when I was in Priſon for not paying the ſame) and ſaid, <hi>She did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Tythe was not due according to the Law of God now in this Goſpel day;</hi> ſhe was made willing to part with me at that time, though I was very dear unto
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:207475:21"/> her as a Husband could be to a Wife, but it was that recompence of Reward which ſhe had an eye unto, and was made willing to ſuffer for, that now through Mercy ſhe hath obtained by Faith; ſhe took great delight in going to Meetings, and entertaining honeſt <hi>Friends;</hi> in the latter end of our time (I ſpeak it to the Praiſe of our God who was ſo good unto us) ſeveral times as we lay in Bed together with broken and contrite Hearts, we did earneſtly deſire of the Lord that he would be pleaſed to give us of his Power and Spirit, that we might ſpend that little time that was yet behind, in his moſt holy Fear and undefiled Way, to the Glory and Praiſe of his Powerful Name; we lived in true Love together, her Company was very pleaſant to me, and I took more delight in it, then in any thing in this World, ſhe ſaid mine was ſo to her; about three or four Weeks before her Death ſhe did Write theſe following Words, <hi>viz. It is the real deſire of my Heart to walk humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, for his Love hath engaged my Heart unto himſelf;</hi> ſhe was one of few Words, (ready to hear, ſlow to ſpeak)
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:207475:21"/> in her Health and in her Sickneſs; and ſo Departed this life like a harmeleſs innocent Lamb, as though ſhe had been a ſleep, ſo good was the Lord unto her at that time, Praiſed be his powerful Name for ever and for evermore, <hi>Amen</hi> ſaith my Soul; much more I might ſay concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her faithful Walking, and tender Care over her Children, to bring them up in the Fear of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She Departed this Life the Thirty firſt day of the Tenth Month, at <hi>Partney-Mills</hi> in <hi>Lincoln-Shire,</hi> in the year 1682. about the Forty eight year of her Age; ſhe lived with me about Thirty years, we had eight Children together, five of them dyed before her; I Buried her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently, and according to good Order practiſed amongſt us, the ſecond day of the eleventh Month, and in the year afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, (being accompanied with a pretty many Friends and Relations) at <hi>Tumby-Wood-ſide,</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Kirkby</hi> on the Baine, in <hi>Friends Burying-Place;</hi> and ſo having ſomewhat eaſed my Spirit, I himbly deſire of the Lord that he would be pleaſed to endue me with his Power and Wiſdom, to Govern my Children
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:207475:22"/> and Family in his moſt holy Fear, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled Way; to the Glory of his moſt holy Name, <hi>Amen;</hi> ſo that when time here in this World will be no more, I may lay down my Head in Peace, as my dear Wife hath done, Praiſes to the Lord over all for ever and for evermore, <hi>Amen</hi> ſaith my Soul.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in great tenderneſs of Spirit, by a lover of Peace and Truth,
<date>the Twenty fourth day of the Eleventh Month, 1682.</date> at <hi>Partney-Mills,</hi> being the place of my out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Habitation,</dateline>
               <signed>Thomas Brown The Elder.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>The Name of the Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſting remembrance.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:207475:22"/>
            <head>This Teſtimony I have to bear concerning <hi>Katharine Brown</hi> my dear Child, it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained as a weight upon my mind for ſeveral days to Write to this effect, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was the care of ſome in days paſt, to keep in remembrance the Words and Works which ſprang from the bleſſed Power of God; and one ſaid, <hi>The Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>The Name of the Righteous was pretious,</hi> &amp;c. This Child, that I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, was from her Childhood very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to go to <hi>Friends Meetings,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as one time it was with me to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine her what ſhe went for, ſhe very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly gave me this anſwer, <hi>To wait upon the Lord,</hi> it was not diſtance of Way, nor difficultneſs of Weather, that did hinder this Child from going to Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and though ſhe was up early, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:207475:23"/> the Journey pretty far, five, ſeven or eight Miles, and went a foot ſometimes, yet this Child was never the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in ſleep or heavineſs that I did perceive, for always when I looked upon her, I found her in a ſolid, ſober and weighty frame of Spirit, which hath cauſed my Heart many a time to rejoyce in the Lord on her behalf; at the time called <hi>Chriſtmaſs,</hi> ſhe went to a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Houſe, they having pretty many Children, and they were playing at Cards, this Child ſat her down by the Fire-ſide, where the Woman of the Houſe was, and ſaid, <hi>Had not thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren better be exerciſed in Reading, &amp;c.</hi> the Woman ſaid, ſhe thought they did no harme, but before this Child was gotten half way home, which was about half a quarter of a Mile, theſe Children fell out as they were at their Game, and were ready to fight, then the Woman remembred the Childs Words, and confeſſed to the truth of them; this Woman came to viſit this Child in the time of her Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and told us this Paſſage. One time it was with her to Write to her Brother <hi>John,</hi> he being ſomething wild,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:207475:23"/> 
               <hi>viz. Dearly beloved Brother, in the Fear of the Lord do I exhort thee, to Leave off Liteneſs and Vanity, and then to wait upon the Lord, and deſire of him to forgive thee that which is paſt,</hi> &amp;c. In the fore end of her Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, one night ſhe being in Bed, and I and her dear Mother alſo in the ſame Room, the Power of the Lord ran through her, and ſhe being very much troubled with a great Hoarſneſs all the time of her Sickneſs, in ſo much that one could hardly hear her ſpeak, but at that time with a very clear voice ſhe broke forth in Praiſing and Magnifying the Lord with a very ſweet Harmony, and ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed and Praiſed be the Lord, for he is gathering a People to himſelf to do his Will, Praiſes to his moſt holy Name for ever,</hi> and kept Praiſing and Magnifying the Lord a pretty time, but her Words were ſomething lower, ſo that we could not hear them all. This Child did take great delight in Reading <hi>Friends Books,</hi> that is, <hi>Epiſtles to Friends,</hi> and in <hi>William Bayly</hi>'s <hi>Book,</hi> and in the Propheſie of the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah,</hi> about the 51ſt Chapter, where God Calls and Exhorts his People to truſt in him; if ſhe had but a little ſpare
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:207475:24"/> time ſhe would imploy it in either Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Writing; ſhe had an excellent Gift in Reading, which greatly comforted and refreſhed moſt that heard her, for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it would take ſuch impreſſion upon the tender-hearted, that Tears would trickle down their Cheeks, for ſhe did read with the Spirit and with the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo; many things more I might men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to her ſober behaviour to all ſhe was concerned with, her comlineſs in her Apparel, a needleſs thing I never did ſee her wear, ſhe hath left a good ſavour behind her, and is gone to her everlaſting Reſt with the Lord for evermore, for ſhe did truly <hi>Remember her Creator in the days of her youth.</hi> She departed this Life the 21ſt day of the <hi>11th</hi> Month, 1680. in the <hi>17th</hi> year of her age, at <hi>Partney-Mills</hi> in <hi>Lincoln-ſhire;</hi> I Buried her decently the <hi>23d</hi> day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at <hi>Tumby-Wood-ſide,</hi> in the pariſh of <hi>Kirkby</hi> upon the <hi>Baine</hi> in <hi>Friends-Burying-place;</hi> ſo deſiring not to be tedious, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſomewhat eaſed my Spirit, I deſire to reſt in peace with the Lord, and in Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with all Men.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in <hi>Partney,</hi> By <hi>Thomas Brown</hi> the Elder.</dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
